Register of the Bailey Willis papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Bailey Willis papers
1916-1943
26011
Willis, Bailey, 1857-1949.
2 manuscript boxes (0.8 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives. Stanford, California 94305-6010
The papers relate to the activities of Stanford University and former Stanford students during World War I, the Tacna-Arica boundary dispute, European topography, and submarine warfare logistics during World War II, in writings, studies, correspondence, and photographs.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1926.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the library catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Materials
Bailey Willis Papers, The Huntington Library
David Starr Jordan Papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Bertram David Wolfe Papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical/Historical Note
March 31, 1857 Born, New York, U.S.
1878-1879 Graduated Columbia University with a degree in mechanical engineering in 1878 and in civil engineering in 1879
1881-1884 Survey geologist for the Northern Pacific Railroad
1884-1915 Worked for the USGS
1889 Named director of the Appalachian division
1893 Author of The Mechanics of Appalachian Structure
1895 to 1902 Lectured on geology at Johns Hopkins University
1900 Appointed as head of the Division of Areal Geology of the United States Geological Survey (USGS)
1903 Led an expedition to northern China, an experience later described in his book Friendly China
1910-1914 Consulted for the government of Argentina, an experience later recorded in his book a Yanqui in Patagonia
1910 Awarded the Gold Medal of the Société de Géographie of France
1915-1922 Professor and chairman of the geology department at Stanford University
1918 Served as chief, Latin American Division, the Inquiry
1920 Elected to the National Academy of the Sciences
1921-1926 Served as a President of the Seismological Society of America
1936 Awarded the Legion of Honor, Belgium
1944 Awarded the Penrose Medal by the Geological Society of America
1949 Died, Palo Alto, California
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers relate to the activities of Stanford University and former Stanford students during World War I, the Tacna-Arica boundary dispute, European topography, and submarine warfare logistics during World War II, in writings, studies, correspondence, and photographs.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Stanford University.; Paris Peace Conference (1919-1920). United States Division of Territorial, Economic and Political Intelligence.; Military topography.; Tacna-Arica question.; World War, 1914-1918--Peace.; World War, 1914-1918--United States.; World War, 1939-1945--Naval operations--Submarine.; Chile--History.; Peru--History.
Collection Contents
- Writings, studies, and reports, 1942-1943 (Box 1-2)
  - "Santa Catarina Island, Brazil, Memorandum for Rear Admiral H. C. Train, Director, Naval Intelligence, Washington, D. C.,", 26 August 1942 (Folder 1: 1)
  - "Servicing Submarines off Brazil, 1-2, Study of Rendezvous between Mother-ship and U-boat, December 1942 - March 1943 ("...under the auspices of the War Service of Stanford University, Professor E. A. Cottrell, chairman, a branch of the Military Intelligence, HQ in San Francisco, Colonel A.E. Ahrends in command)," (Folder 1: 2-3)
  - "Servicing Submarines in the Atlantic," sequel to "Servicing Submarines off Brazil,", circa 1943 (Folder 1: 4)
  - "Gulf Weed and Submarine, Study For General Arnold and Admiral Train,", February 1943 (Folder 1: 5)
  - "Servicing Submarines on the West Coast of Africa, Study of Rendezvous between Mother-ship and U-boat,", July 1943 (Folder 1: 6)
  - "Northern Adriatic; Coast of Dalmatia, Fiume to Zengg, Istrian Peninsula, Illustrated by Photographs taken in 1905,", September 1943 (Folder 1: 7)
  - "Italy; Bologna and Florence, Illustrated by Photographs taken in 1905,", September 1943 (Folder 1: 8)
  - "The Lower Danube; the Iron Gate, Illustrated by Photographs taken in 1905,", September 1943. (Folder 2: 1)
    (Excerpt from Topography and Strategy in the War, H. Holt, 1917)
  - "Notes on the Valleys of the Apennines, Illustrating the Occurrences of the Terraces in Relation to Defense,", September 1943 (Folder 2: 2)
  - "Karpathian Mountains in Galicia, Illustrated by Photographs taken in 1905,", October 1943 (Folder 2: 3)
  - "Danube above Vienna, Illustrated by Photographs taken in 1905 and Engravings,", October 1943 (Folder 2: 4)
  - "Public Utilities Committee General Plan for the Occupation of Manila, Seminar-project of the Naval School of Military Government and Administration," Columbia University, November 1943 (Folder 2: 5)
- Correspondence, 1916-1943 (Box 2)
  - Defense Council correspondence with the Department of Geology, 1916-1918 (Folder 2: 6)
  - Letters from students of the Department of Geology who went to the War, 1916-1919 (Folder 2: 7-8)
  - Santa Cruz Military Survey by Department of Geology, 1917-1932. (Folder 2: 9)
    Includes memoranda
  - Letter to Charles E. Hughes on Tacna-Arica controversy, 7 February 1923. (Folder 2: 10)
    Includes photos of Tacna, Peru, 1923
  - Letter from Pierre Denis to Bailey Willis, 2 October 1924 (Folder 2: 11)
  - Letters to be placed with the Reports for Military Intelligence and Strategic Services, 1941-1943 (Folder 2: 12)